Bedau, Hugo A.; Papers apap199
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Hugo A. Bedau Papers
1954-2005
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
apap199
36 cubic ft.
Hugo A. Bedau (Ph.D., Harvard, 1961) is a commentator, scholar, and activist for the abolition of capital punishment. He is a prominent spokesperson in the abolitionist movement and well-known for his scholarship and writing concerning the death penalty and the challenge to separate logical arguments from moral arguments.
Biographical Sketch
Hugo A. Bedau (Ph.D., Harvard, 1961) is a commentator, scholar, and activist for the abolition of capital punishment. He is a prominent spokesperson in the abolitionist movement and well-known for his scholarship and writing concerning the death penalty and the challenge to separate logical arguments from moral arguments.
Bedau completed his undergraduate degree at the University of Redlands in 1949, did his graduate work at Boston University, and attained his doctorate in 1961 from Harvard University. [Who's Who in America. 62nd ed. 2008]. Before getting his doctorate, Bedau worked as an instructor and lecturer at Dartmouth College and Princeton University as his growing interest in death penalty issues led to an offer to serve on the Board of Directors of the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment. In 1961, Bedau completed the doctoral program and was soon hired as an Associate Professor at Reed College where he stayed from 1962-1966. During this time he published his first book, The Death Penalty in America: An Anthology (1962), that is currently in its 4th edition.
In 1966, Bedau was hired as Professor of Philosophy at Tufts University where spent the next thirty-three years as he helped found the Center for the Study of Decision Making. Among his scholarly work, Bedau is the author of the Courts, the Constitution and Capital Punishment (1977); Death is Different (1987); co-author, In Spite of Innocence (1992); editor, Civil Disobedience in Focus (1991); Current Issues and Enduring Questions (4th edition, 1996); co-editor, Capital Punishment in the United States (1976); and a contributor to many other volumes. He has also written books about writing such as Critical Thinking, Reading, and Writing (2nd edition, 1996). His Romanell - Phi Beta Kappa lectures delivered at Tufts in the spring of 1995, were published by Oxford University Press under the title, Making Moral Choices. [Hugo Adam Bedau. Tufts Philosophy http://ase.tufts.edu/philosophy/people/bedau.shtml]. In addition, he has published hundreds of articles, essays, and commentaries on capital punishment.
In addition to his scholarship, Bedau has been active in the capital punishment abolition movement for many decades. He was the chairman of the board for the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (NCADP) and a board member for the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) of Massachusetts, the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment and several other organizations. He has also been a long time member of the Massachusetts Citizens Against the Death Penalty (MCADP) and an active member of such organizations as the NAACP Legal Defense Fund, Amnesty International, the American Philosophical Association, American Association of University Professors, and the American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy. Bedau has frequently testified before state and federal legislative committees as an expert on the issue of capital punishment and has advocated for Death Row inmates, such as Harold "Wili" Otey who was executed in 1994 in Nebraska.
Bedau married his second wife Constance Elizabeth Putnam in 1990. In 1992, she co-authored In Spite of Innocence with Bedau and Michael Radelet. [Who's Who in America. 62nd ed. 2008]. Bedau has four children from his first marriage: Lauren, Mark Adam, Paul Hugo, and Guy Anthony, as well as four grandchildren. [Who's Who in America. 62nd ed. 2008 and Hugo Adam Bedau. Tufts Philosophy http://ase.tufts.edu/philosophy/people/bedau.shtml]. After retiring from Tufts in 1999, Bedau has continued writing, speaking and working for the abolition of capital punishment.
On August 13, 2012 Hugo Bedau passed away at the age of 85. [New York Times Obituary. Last accessed September 24, 2012. http://www.nytimes.com/2012/08/17/us/hugo-bedau-philosopher-who-opposed-death-penalty-dies-at-85.html].
Chronology of Events:
1926 Born in Portland, Oregon on September 23
1944 Graduated from high school in San Francisco
1944 Entered the Naval Officer Training at the University of Southern California
1949 Received a bachelor's degree (summa cum laude) from the University of Redlands in California
1951 Received a master's degree from Boston University
1952 Married Jan Lisbeth Peterson Mastin (Divorced 1988)
1953 Received a second master's degree from Harvard
1953-1954 Instructor at Dartmouth
1954-1957 Instructor at Princeton
1957-1958 Danforth Fellow
1958-1961 Lecturer at Princeton
1959 Began serving on the Board of Directors of the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment (he served until 1972)
1961 Received a Ph. D from Harvard, he also did graduate work at Boston University
1961-1962 Liberal Arts Fellow in Law and Philosophy Harvard University Law School.
1962-1966 Associate Professor at Reed College
1964 Published his first book The Death Penalty in America. In 1997, a 4 th edition of the book was published.
1967-1997 Professor of Philosophy at Tufts University
1969-1972 President of the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment (Served until 1972)
1980 Visiting Life Fellow at Clare Hall, Cambridge University
1981 Served as Vice President of the American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy.
1981 Visiting Professor of Law at the University of Natal in South Africa
1984-1998 Served on the Board of Directors of American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), Massachusetts
1987 Served as Vice President of the ACLU, Massachusetts
1988 Visiting fellow at Wolfson College, Oxford.
1989 Received the Abolitionist Award from the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty
1990 Married Constance Elizabeth Putnam
1990-1993 Chairman, Board for the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (NCADP)
1994 Visiting Professor of Law at University of Westminster, London.
1994-5 Received the Phi-Beta Kappa Romanell Professorship in Philosophy
1997 Received the August Vollmer Award from the American Society of Criminology
1997-1999, 2003-2004 Honorary Research Fellow -Bantham Project- University of London
1926 Born in Portland, Oregon on September 23
1944 Graduated from high school in San Francisco
1944 Entered the Naval Officer Training at the University of Southern California
1949 Received a bachelor's degree (summa cum laude) from the University of Redlands in California
1951 Received a master's degree from Boston University
1952 Married Jan Lisbeth Peterson Mastin (Divorced 1988)
1953 Received a second master's degree from Harvard
1953-1954 Instructor at Dartmouth
1954-1957 Instructor at Princeton
1957-1958 Danforth Fellow
1958-1961 Lecturer at Princeton
1959 Began serving on the Board of Directors of the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment (he served until 1972)
1961 Received a Ph. D from Harvard, he also did graduate work at Boston University
1961-1962 Liberal Arts Fellow in Law and Philosophy Harvard University Law School.
1962-1966 Associate Professor at Reed College
1964 Published his first book The Death Penalty in America. In 1997, a 4 th edition of the book was published.
1967-1997 Professor of Philosophy at Tufts University
1969-1972 President of the American League to Abolish Capital Punishment (Served until 1972)
1980 Visiting Life Fellow at Clare Hall, Cambridge University
1981 Served as Vice President of the American Society for Political and Legal Philosophy.
1981 Visiting Professor of Law at the University of Natal in South Africa
1984-1998 Served on the Board of Directors of American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), Massachusetts
1987 Served as Vice President of the ACLU, Massachusetts
1988 Visiting fellow at Wolfson College, Oxford
1989 Received the Abolitionist Award from the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty
1990 Married Constance Elizabeth Putnam
1990-1993 Chairman, Board for the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (NCADP)
1994 Visiting Professor of Law at University of Westminster, London
1994-5 Received the Phi-Beta Kappa Romanell Professorship in Philosophy
1997 Received the August Vollmer Award from the American Society of Criminology
1997-1999, 2003-2004 Honorary Research Fellow -Bantham Project- University of London
Scope and Contents
The Hugo A. Bedau Papers encompasses a lifetime of research, scholarship, and political activism regarding the issue of capital punishment. All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries' M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Hugo A. Bedau in 2002 as part of the National Death Penalty Archive. The collection is arranged into four series: Series 1: Scholarship and Teaching; Series 2: Correspondence; Series 3: Advocacy Organization; and Series 4: Subject Files.
The Bedau Papers are a valuable resource to scholars, students and historians studying the controversial and politically volatile subject of capital punishment from 1955 -2002. The records in this collection reflect Bedau's commitment as a leading academic and activist challenging the fundamental legality of the death penalty. The entire collection, totaling nearly 37 cubic feet, contains Bedau's drafts, reprints, correspondence, writings and unpublished work, conference materials, newsletters, records from advocacy organizations, and capital punishment case files.
Series 1 is devoted to Bedau's scholarly writings including manuscripts, journal articles, book chapters, opinion pieces, and transcripts of testimonies Bedau gave to state and federal legislatures. Of note are unpublished works such as drafts, notes, studies, proposals, reports, conference papers, lectures, grant proposals and reports. This series also features Bedau and Michael Radelet's Miscarriages of Justice in Potentially Capital Cases including drafts, professional critiques, testimonies, correspondence, notes, and news clippings.
Series 2 contains a tremendous amount of correspondence with many of Bedau's colleagues such as: Anthony Amsterdam, William Bowers, Peggy Davis, Watt Espy, Gerald Gottlieb, David Kendall, Douglas Lyons, Philip Mackey, Michael Radelet, Marc Riedel, Victor Streib, Neil Vidmar, Marvin Wolfgang, and Franklyn Zimring. This series begins in 1957 and continues for Bedau's entire career.
Reflecting Bedau's work with abolition organizations, Series 3 contains minutes of meetings, project files, newsletters, press packets, correspondence, event and conference material for many abolitionist groups such as the National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (NCADP), Massachusetts Citizens Against the Death Penalty (MCADP), Amnesty International, American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), and the Legal Defense Fund. The collection also contains various newsletters, press packets, correspondence, and information about many other regional organizations including: the Alabama Committee to Abolish the Death Penalty, Murder Victims Families for Reconciliation, Detention Ministry and the Colorado Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty.
Series 4 contains research material and newspaper clippings collected by Bedau and covers more than 40 years of capital punishment issues and cases of interest to him. This series closely follows Bedau's original arrangement schemes of organization by location, case and subject and contains a diverse collection of news clippings, journal articles, and court decisions.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized as follows: 1. Scholarship and Teaching, 1958-2002; 2. Correspondence, 1957-2003; 3. Advocacy Organization, 1958-2003; 4. Subject Files, 1955-2003
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were transferred to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Hugo A. Bedau in 2002.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Death Penalty; Criminal Justice and Prisons; Capital punishment--United States; Death row; Punishment--Moral and ethical aspects; Criminal law; Correspondence; Manuscripts for publication; Notes; Minutes; Newsletters; Clippings, newspaper; Sound recordings; Videotape recordings (video recordings); Amnesty International; National Coalition to Abolish the Death Penalty (U.S.); Death Penalty Information Center (U.S.); American Civil Liberties Union; Massachusetts Citizens Against the Death Penalty
- Scholarship and Teaching, 1958-2002; 1; 6 cubic ft.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains drafts and reprints of the works of Hugo Bedau. They are organized first by format and then alphabetically by title. Formats include journal articles, newspaper articles, pamphlets, book chapters, lectures, and encyclopedia articles. Also included are materials related to various conferences Bedau attended.
  - Journal Articles, 1965-2002; 1.1
    This subseries contains drafts and reprints of journal articles written by Bedau.
    - "The 1964 Death Penalty Referendum in Oregon Some Notes from a Participant-Observer".Crime and Delinquency, 1980 October (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 1)
    - "American Populism and the Death Penalty: Witnesses at an Execution".Howard Journal of Criminal Justice, 1994 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 2)
    - "Bentham's Utilitarian Critique of the Death Penalty".The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 3)
    - "Bentham's Utilitarian Critique of the Death Penalty".The Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 4)
    - "Berger's Defense of the Death Penalty: How not to Read the Constitution".Michigan Law Review, 1983 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 5)
    - Capital Punishment Issue of the American Journal of Orthopsychiatry -- edited by Hugo Bedau and Chester Piece (see: Capital Punishment in the United States), 1975 July (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 6)
    - "Capital Punishment in Oregon, 1903-1964".Oregon Law Review, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 7)
    - "The Choice Between Imprisonment and Death".Albany Law Review, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 8)
    - "The Courts, the Constitution and Capital Punishment". (39 pages)Utah Law Review, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 9)
    - "The Courts, the Constitution and Capital Punishment". (39 pages)Utah Law Review, 1968 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 10)
    - "The Death Penalty as a Deterrent Argument and Evidence". Ethics 1970, also published as "Deterrence and the Death Penalty: a Reconsideration".The Journal of Criminal Law, Northwestern University, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 11)
    - "The Death Penalty as a Deterrent Argument and Evidence". Ethics 1970, also published as "Deterrence and the Death Penalty: a Reconsideration".The Journal of Criminal Law, Northwestern University, 1971 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 12)
    - "The Death Penalty in America -- Review and Forecast".Federal Probation, 1971 June (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 13)
    - "The Death Penalty: Yesterday and Today".Dickerson Law Review, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 14)
    - "The Death Penalty in America: Yesterday, Today and Tomorrow".The Iliff Review, 1988 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 15)
    - "The Death Penalty in the United States: Background and Developments".Natal University Law Review, 1981 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 16)
    - "The Death Penalty: Social Policy and Social Justice". Arizona State Law Journal, 1977 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 17)
    - "Death Sentences in New Jersey 1907-1960". (64 pages) Rutgers Law Review, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 18)
    - "Death Sentences in New Jersey 1907-1960". (64 pages) Rutgers Law Review, 1965 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 19)
    - "The Decline of Executive Clemency in Capital Cases".New York University Review of Law and Social Change, 1990-1991 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 20)
    - "The Execution of the Innocent".Law and Contemporary Problems, 1998 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 21)
    - "Felony Murder Rape and the Mandatory death Penalty: A Study in Discretionary Justice".Suffolk University Law Review, 1976 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 22)
    - "Furman's Wake in the Land of Bean and Cod".The Prison Journal, 1974 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 23)
    - "Greg v. Georgia and the 'New Death Penalty".Criminal Justice Ethics -- John Jay College, 1985 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 24)
    - "How to Argue About the Death Penalty".Israel Law Review, 1991 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 25)
    - "Imprisonment vs. Death: Does Avoiding Schwarzschild's Paradox Lead to Sheleff's Dilemma?"Albany Law Review, 1990 (Box 1 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 26)
    - "The Minimal Invasion Argument against the Death Penalty".Criminal Justice -- John Jay College, 2002 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 1)
    - "A Moral Reading of the Eighth Amendment".Thomas M. Cooley Law Review, 1996 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 2)
    - "The Nixon Administration and the Deterrent Effect of the Death Penalty".University of Pittsburgh Law Review, 1973 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 3)
    - "Objections to the Death Penalty from the Moral Point of View". Revue Internationale de Broit Penal, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 4)
    - "The Problem of Capital Punishment".Current History, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 5)
    - "A Social Philosopher Looks at the Death Penalty"American Journal of Psychiatrics, 1967 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 6)
    - "Thinking of the Death Penalty as Cruel and Unusual Punishment". (52 pages)U.C. Davis Law Review, 1985 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 7)
    - "Thinking of the Death Penalty as Cruel and Unusual Punishment". (52 pages)U.C. Davis Law Review, 1985 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 8)
  - Newspaper/Magazine/Newsletter Articles and Essays, 1957-1993; 1.2
    This subseries contains drafts and reprints of shorter published works written by Bedau.
    - "After the Killing Comes the Rage". The Boston Globe, 1989 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 9)
    - "Are Mandatory Capital Sentences Inherently Discriminatory", the Jewish Advocate, 1975 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 10)
      Also published as "Still Cruel and Unusual", The Nation, 1975.
    - "Capital Punishment: Pros and Cons".New York Newsday, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 11)
    - "The Case Against the Death Penalty".The New Leader, 1959 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 12)
    - The Case Against the Death Penalty".Georgia Journal of Corrections, 1974 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 13)
    - "A Condemned Man's Last Wish: Organ Donation and a 'Meaningful Death'".Hastings Center Report, 1979 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 14)
    - "Cruel and Unusual Punishment".Christian Social Action, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 15)
    - "Death in the Name of Law".Tufts Criterion, 1982 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 16)
    - "The Death Penalty and State Constitutional Rights in the United States of America"Crime Prevention and Criminal Justice Newsletter, 1986 November (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 17)
    - "The Eighth Amendment the Death Penalty", The Bill of Rights Journal, 1987 December (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 18)
    - Letter to the Editor Reconstruction, 1993 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 19)
    - Miscellaneous Essays, 1959-1964 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 20)
    - "Murder and the Death Penalty in the 1980s".MCADP News, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 21)
    - "New Life for the Death Penalty".The Nation, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 22)
    - "Playing a Lethal Lottery".City Issues -- Newsletter of Boston's Episcopal City 1990 Mission (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 23)
    - "The Politics of Capital Punishment". the Recorder San Francisco, 1990 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 24)
    - "The Politics of Death".Boston After Dark, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 25)
    - "The Politics of Death".Trial Magazine, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 26)
    - "Reflections on the Morality of the Death Penalty".The Defender -- New York State Defenders Association, 1986 July-1986 August (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 27)
    - "The Right to Die by Firing Squad".The Hastings Center Report, 1977 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 28)
    - "Should We Let Gilmore Decide his own Fate?" Boston Globe, 1976 November (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 29)
    - "SJC Voids State Death Penalty Statute; Legislature Mulls Constitutional Amendment".The Docket -- Civil Liberties Union of Massachusetts, 1976 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 30)
    - "Someday McCleskey Will Be Death Penalty's Dred Scott".Los Angeles Times, 1987 May (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 31)
    - "The Struggle for Law Reform".New Jersey State Bar Journal, 1962 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 32)
    - "Supreme Court Challenged by 8th Amendment Death Penalty Pleas".Jewish Advocate, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 33)
    - "What Price Exacting the Greatest Punishment?" by Hugo Bedau and Richard Moran.Boston Sunday Globe, 1997 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 34)
    - "We Prevented an Execution".New York World Telegram and the Sun, 1960 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 35)
  - Unpublished or Unidentified works, 1958-1993; Undated; 1.3
    This subseries contains drafts of works by Bedau and hand written notes which he may or may not have later published.
    - The Right to Life and other Essays on the Death Penalty, 1967 proposal (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 36)
    - 8th Amendment Argument Essay Notes, 1972 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 37)
    - "The Eighth Amendment, Human Dignity, and the Death Penalty", possibly unpublished, ca. 1989 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 38)
    - "The Death Penalty and the Right to Kill", unpublished, 1987 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 39)
    - Notes on Capital Punishment Worldwide, ca. 1962 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 40)
    - Notes on New Jersey History of Capital Punishment Research, 1958 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 41)
    - Notes on New Jersey History of Capital Punishment Research, 1958 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 42)
    - Notes, 1971 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 43)
    - Notes, 1982-1983 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 44)
    - Untitled article --Hands Off Cain Magazine, Undated (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 45)
    - Untitled article -- submitted to NJ State Bar Journal, ca. 1958 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 46)
    - Untitled essay, ca. 1959 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 47)
    - Untitled journal article on Clemency, ca. 1990 (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 48)
    - Untitled work -- possibly a postscript (original folder titled HAB epilogue), Undated (Box 2 (1-Scholarship and Teaching), Folder 49)
  - Studies/Proposals/Reports, 1958-1999; 1.4